Guide to the Mahmoud Hammad Collection AD.MC.091
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Mahmoud Hammad Collection
1939-2017
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Hammad, Mahmoud (Syrian artist, 1923-1988)
Hammad, Lubna (1960- )
AD.MC.091
1600 Digital Objects
Exhibition-related materials, press clippings, writings, correspondence, biographical documents, professional documents, photographs, and sketches belonging to Syrian artist and educator Mahmoud Hammad (1923-1988), as well as some related material pertaining to his wife, fellow artist Durriya Fakhoury Hammad (1930-2015). First assembled and organized by his daughter, Lubna Hammad.
The materials were received in good condition, which enabled the digitization to take place on-site at al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art, NYUAD. Digital surrogates were created for all collection items. Upon digitization, all materials were returned to the owner. Materials were rehoused in archival enclosures as needed.
E-records AD_MC_091
Content Description
The Mahmoud Hammad collection consists of exhibition-related materials, press clippings, writings, correspondence, biographical documents, documents generated in the context of work as a teacher and administrator in Damascus, Syria, photographs documenting his life and works, and some sketches and preparatory drawings. It also features materials pertaining to his wife, the late artist Durriya Fakhoury Hammad (1930-2015). The collection offers detailed insight into the terms and conditions of creative practice in Syria in the decades following the country's independence in 1946. Particularly rich are materials related to Hammad's career as an educator with a leading role at the Faculty of Fine Art in Damascus, where he advocated for the rights of artists to engage in formal experimentation, took study trips to assess contemporary trends and best practices, and produced teaching materials having to do with art theory and technique. Also represented are sketches and plans pertaining to Hammad's design work and slides documenting his paintings, medals, and other works of art. The majority of the materials are in Arabic, although many exhibition materials are bilingual (often Arabic and French). Some material is in Italian, reflecting the fact that Hammad studied at the Accademia di Belle Arti (1953-1957) and subsequently maintained ties to Italian artists and critics.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series: (I) Exhibition materials, 1950s - 2001; (II) Press clippings; (III) Writings by Hammad (published and unpublished); (IV) Commercial and commissioned design work; (V) Correspondence and personal papers; (VI) Photographic materials; (VII) Other items in the possession of the artist. Those series that contain digital objects accessible online are often subdivided by type or decade, and are then usually arranged in chronological order within subseries.
Custodial History
These materials are part of the family estate of Mahmoud Hammad (1923-1988) in the custody of Lubna Mahmoud Hammad in Amman. They were assembled by the artist himself during his lifetime and maintained in his home and studio in Damascus, Syria, as records and documents pertaining to his professional life as a painter, a professor and subsequently Dean and higher administrator at the Faculty of Fine Arts (Kulliyat al-Funun) in the University of Damascus, and as a public figure engaged in cultural programs and discussion in Syria. Following the death of Mahmoud Hammad and the relocation of his widow, the artist Durriya [Derrieh] Fakhoury Hammad (1930-2015), to the residence of Lubna Hammad in Amman, the materials were transported over time to Jordan. By 2014, the bulk of the collection had been consolidated in Amman at Lubna's residence with only a very few items such as plaster carvings and molds remaining behind in Syria. Over the past decade, Lubna has worked on organizing and scanning the archive and has built a database cataloging the items. The organization of the materials reflects Lubna's cataloging labor, in which she is guided by her intimate knowledge of her parents' lives and careers as artists.
The materials were digitized on-site at al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art, NYUAD. The first batch was completed in January 2022 and a sixth was undertaken in July 2023. Further accretions are expected.
Biographical / Historical
Mahmoud Hammad (1923-1988) was a foundational contributor to the formation of modern art institutions in Syria. Trained in both painting and printmaking, he worked across media over the course of his career: as a painter, a printmaker, a medal engraver and a sculptor. He drew the admiration of other Syrian artists for his in-depth knowledge of compositional methods and color properties. His knowledge of technique made him a consummate educator and from 1960 until his death in 1988 he not only taught painting at the Faculty of Fine Arts (Kulliyat al-Funun al-Jamila) in Damascus but also rose to become head of the department, followed by serving as Dean of the school.
Born in 1923, Hammad completed primary school at the Italian School of Damascus and secondary school at the prestigious Jawdat al Hashemi school. At the age of sixteen, Hammad traveled to Italy for a study trip. Throughout the 1940s he participated in group exhibitions organized by emergent civic organizations, including helping to establish the Studio Veronese in Damascus (est. 1941) and participating in the Association of Syrian Artists, based in the neighborhood of Abu Rummana, in the 1950s. Hammad was an early recipient of a binational fellowship to complete a degree at the Accademia di Belle Arti in Rome. He studied abroad in Italy from 1953 to 1957, there participating in numerous exhibitions and prize competitions. Upon his return to Syria, he fulfilled his fellowship obligations by teaching art for two years in Daraa, to the south of Damascus (1958–1960). The two years he spent in this rural community are sometimes described as a period of social realism, or as his "Houran period," referring to his interest in depicting the conditions of the agricultural region and its laborers.
The 1960s were a significant decade for Hammad's career as well as for the development of an arts infrastructure in Syria. Hammad was among the first Syrians hired to teach at the Faculty of Fine Art upon its creation in 1960 and its formalization as a degree-granting faculty in 1962. He helped to recruit an international cohort of artists to teach at the Faculty and advocated in the press for the value of a modern curriculum integrating studies in formal experimentation and abstract composition in addition to academic realist techniques. Over the same decade, his own painting took an abstract turn. He exhibited compositions derived from the formal qualities of Arabic writing in major international exhibitions, including the São Paulo Art Biennial and the Venice Biennale.
Around 1963, Hammad began to exhibit a type of painting that became his most recognized achievement as an artist: painterly compositions based on the modern, artistic manipulation of the letter forms of the Arabic language (later to be dubbed horoufiyah, or ḥurūfiyya). Because Hammad first exhibited his experiments in this vein in the early 1960s, he predated the pan-regional 1970s florescence of Arab artists seeking to incorporate Arabic writing into fine art compositions. For his work with Arabic writing as a basis for painterly compositions, he is considered a pioneer of not only Syrian modern art but also Arab art in the twentieth century.
In 1967, he won a grant from UNESCO as a creative artist, and in 1969 was awarded the State Prize for Fine Arts. Along with Professor Abdo Kass-hout, in 1979, he won the competition to design "The Unknown Soldier" monument in Damascus, which was built and completed in 1994. His works are preserved in the National Museum of Damascus, the Ministry of Culture and Foreign Affairs, and in private art collections in Syria, Lebanon, Egypt, Iraq, Italy, France, Switzerland, Yugoslavia, Russia, and the United States of America.
Hammad died in 1988 in Damascus, Syria.
Lubna Hammad is an architect based in Amman, Jordan. The daughter of the late artist Mahmoud Hammad, she is responsible for the artist's estate, including both his works of art and his archival papers. She maintains the artist website, http://www.mahmoudhammad.com/. In November 2022 she participated in a program at the Abu Dhabi Art Fair organized by al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art, "Saloua Raouda Choucair & Mahmoud Hammad - Preserving a Legacy: Custodians of Arab Art."
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Items were borrowed from Lubna Hammad for the purposes of digitization, then returned.
Conditions Governing Access
Digital surrogates only are held by the repository. Materials not made available online may be consulted in person at al Mawrid in the NYUAD library. Researchers should contact nyuad.almawrid@nyu.edu to request details or to make an appointment.
Related Materials
A parallel collection of digitized materials in the estate of Mahmoud Hammad may be found in the Modern Art Syria Archive maintained by the Atassi Foundation for Arts and Culture, https://www.atassifoundation.com/masa-collections
Selected bibliography:
1. Ali, Wijdan. Modern Islamic Art: Development and Continuity. Gainesville: University Press of Florida, 1997.
2. Allun, ʿAbd al ʿAzīz. Munʿaṭaf al Sitīnāt fi Tārīkh al Funūn al Jamīla al Muʿaṣira fī Sūriya. Damascus, Syria: Culture House for the International Daadoush Group, 2003.
3. Atassi, Mouna, and Samir Sayegh. Contemporary Art in Syria, 1898-1998. Damascus, Syria: Gallery Atassi, 1998.
4. Dagher, Charbel. Art and Identity: Arabic Hurufiyya. Trans. Samir Mahmoud. Milan: Skira, 2016.
5. Hammad, Lubna. "A History of Art Associations in Damascus During the 20th Century: From Emergence Until the First Arab Conference of Fine Arts in Damascus in 1971." Trans. Basel Jbaily. Atassi Foundation Journal, no. 8 (October 5, 2020), https://www.atassifoundation.com/the-journal/issue-8-damascus2
6. Kashlan, Mamdouh. Niṣf Qarn min al-Ibdaʿ al-Tashkīlī fī Sūriya. Damascus: Ebla Gallery, 2006.
7. Lenssen, Anneka. "The Plasticity of the Syrian Avant-Garde, 1964-1970," ARTMargins 2, no. 2 (June 2013): 43–70.
8. —. Beautiful Agitation: Modern Painting and Politics in Syria. Oakland: University of California Press, 2020.
9. Lenssen, Anneka, Sarah Rogers, and Nada Shabout, eds. Modern Art in the Arab World: Primary Documents. New York: Museum of Modern Art, 2018.
10. Shabout, Nada. Modern Arab Art: Formation of Arab Aesthetics. Gainesville: University Press of Florida, 2007.
11. Al-Sharīf, Tāriq. ʿIshrūn Fannānan min Sūriya. Damascus: Ministry of Culture, 1972.
Art, Arab; Art -- Arab countries; Art, Arab -- 20th century; Art, Syrian; Art, Syrian -- 20th century; Art, Syrian – 20th century – Exhibitions; Painting, Syrian -- 20th century; Artists–Syria; Hurufiyya; Art archives; Damascus (Syria); Rome (Italy); Hammad, Mahmoud (Syrian artist, 1923-1988); Hammad, Lubna (1960- ); Fakhoury, Durriya (Durriya Fakhoury Hammad) (1930-2015); Faculty of Fine Arts, Damascus University; Damascus University; Accademia di belle arti (Rome, Italy); Sursock Museum
- Series I: Exhibition materials, 1950s - 2001 (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - I.A. Solo and group exhibitions featuring Mahmoud Hammad (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Scope and Contents
    Materials include catalogs, brochures, and invitations pertaining to art exhibitions in which Hammad participated, most of which were held in Syria. Others were held in various locations, including France, Germany, Lebanon, Turkey, and the USSR. The majority of the materials are in Arabic and/or French, with a few items in other languages, including German, Russian, Serbian, Polish, and Turkish.
    - 1. A list of the artworks in Mahmoud Hammad's exhibition with the Arab Association of Fine Arts, Damascus, 1944 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 2. A list of the artworks in an exhibition of Mahmoud Hammad, 1945 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 3. "[Exhibition of Paintings by Nasir Shoura and Mahmoud Hammad]," Damascus, 1951 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 4. "[Exhibition of Paintings by Mahmoud Hammad]," Damascus, 1953 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 5. Image of the painting by Mahmoud Hammad awarded Second Prize at the Fourth Exhibition of Fine Arts in Damascus, 1953 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 6. "Salon d'Automne," Damascus, 1962 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 7. "Salon d'Automne," Damascus, 1963 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 8. "Salon d'Automne," Damascus, 1965 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 9. "[Exhibition of Shoura, Hammad, Moudarres, Zayat]," Damascus, 1965 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 10. "[Contemporary Syrian Painting]," Beirut, 1966 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 11. "Salon d'Automne," Damascus, 1967 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 12. "[Paintings from Travel]," Paris, 1967 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 13. "Hammad," Beirut, 1968 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 14. "Hammad," Damascus, 1968 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 15. "[Exhibition of Contemporary Syrian Painting]," Belgrade, 1968 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 16. "[Exhibition of the Role of Art in the Battle of Steadfastness and Armed Struggle]," Damascus, 1968 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 17. "[The Art Exhibition to Support the Operations of the Fedayee]," Damascus, 1969 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 18. "[Fifth Traveling Exhibition in the Governorates]," multiple locations in Syria, 1969 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 19. "[Exhibition of Paintings by Mahmoud Hammad]," Yerevan, 1969 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 20. "[Shoura — Hammad]," Damascus, 1970 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 21. "[The First Exhibition of the Fine Arts Syndicate]," Damascus, 1971 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 22. "[Six Syrian Artists]," Damascus, 1972 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 23. "[Mahmoud Hammad: Retrospective Exhibition]," Damascus, 1972 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 24. "[Exhibition of Features of Contemporary Syrian Arab Art]," Damascus, 1974 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 25. "[The Fourth Annual General Exhibition of the Artists of the Syrian Arab Country]," Damascus, 1974 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 26. "[Features of Syrian Arab Art, 1879-1975]," Damascus, 1975 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 27. "[Traveling Exhibition of Artists from the Syrian Arab Country]," multiple locations, 1975-1976 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 28. "[Artwork by Artists of the Syrian Arab Republic]," multiple locations, 1976 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 29. "[Syria-Italy, Civilizational Links: Exhibition of Syrian Artists Who Completed Their Studies in Italy]," Damascus, 1976 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 30. Intergrafik exhibition, Berlin, 1976 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 31. "[Exhibition in Homage to the Thirteenth Anniversary of the Revolution]," Damascus, 1976 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 32. "[Traveling Exhibition of Artists from the Syrian Arab Country]," multiple locations, 1976-1977 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 33. Exhibition of Mahmoud Hammad, Abdul Karim Faraj, Ahmad Al Ahmad, Suwalki, 1978 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 34. "[Exhibition of Six Painters from Syria]," Damascus, 1979 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 35. "[Contemporary Oil Painting in Syria]," Paris, circa 1980s (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 36. "[Exhibition of Artists: Abdulkader Arnaout, Mamoud Hammad, Elias Zayat, Nasir Shoura, Nazir Nabaa]," Damascus, 1980 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 37. "[Annual Exhibition for the Artists of the Country]," Damascus, 1980 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 38. Exhibition of Syrian oil paintings for the Syrian Arab Cultural Week, Tunis, 1981 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 39. "[Exhibition of Printmaking]," Damascus, 1981 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 40. "[Six Artists from Syria]," Paris, 1981 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 41. "[Annual Exhibition of Plastic Art in Syria]," Damascus, 1981 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 42. "[Paintings by Hammad]," Damascus, 1982 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 43. "[Exhibition of Plastic Art in the Syrian Arab Country]," Damascus, 1983 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 44. Exhibition at Ugarit Gallery, Damascus, 1983 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 45. Exhibition at Ugarit Gallery, Damascus, 1983 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 46. "[Hammad]," Damascus, 1985 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 47. "[Painting: Syrian Arab Republic]," Berlin, 1985 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 48. "[Annual Exhibition of Plastic Art in Syria]," Damascus, 1985 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 49. "[Contemporary Syrian Plastic Art]," Beiteddine, 1985 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 50. Group exhibition, Damascus, 1986 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 51. "[Syrian Contemporary Art]," Tripoli, Lebanon, 1986 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 52. "[Annual Exhibition of Plastic Art in Syria]," Damascus, likely 1986 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 53. Exhibition of manuscripts, rare books, and paintings inspired by Arab heritage, Damascus, 1987 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 54. "International Nasreddin Hodja Festival, 1st International Cartoon Competition," Konya, 1988 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 55. Group exhibition at Comfortium Gallery, 1988 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 56. "[Al-Karama Exhibition]," Damascus, 1988 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 57. "[The Late Artist Mahmoud Hammad]," Damascus, 1988 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 58. "[The Second Annual Exhibition for the Professors of the Faculty of Fine Arts]," Damascus, 1990 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 59. Exhibition of Fateh al-Moudarres, Mahmoud Hammad, Louay Kayyali, Damascus, 1993 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 60. "Modern and Contemporary Syrian Art: Vibrant Explorations," circa 1996 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 61. Group exhibition on the occasion of the visit of Pope John II, Damascus, 2001 (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - I.B. Exhibitions not featuring Mahmoud Hammad (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Materials include items collected in the course of Mahmoud Hammad's visits to and/or personal connection to other people's exhibitions. Durriya Hammad participated in the Exhibition of Women Artists from the Syrian Arab Country, 1975.
    - 1. "[Adham Ismail]," Damascus, 1964 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 2. "[Exhibition of Women Artists from the Syrian Arab Country]," Damascus, 1975 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 3. "[Photographs by M. Roumi]," Damascus, after 1986 (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - I.C. Publications about art organizations and activities (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Subseries contains materials documenting institutions and sites of exhibition and/or artistic training, collected by Hammad.
    - 1. "[The Applied Arts]," Damascus, 1964 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 2. "[Faculty of Fine Arts, University of Damascus]," Damascus, 1972 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 3. "[Guide to the Faculty of Fine Arts]," Damascus, 1972 - 1973 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 4. "[Faculty of Fine Arts]," Damascus, 1973 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    - 5. Non-periodical publication of the Fine Arts Syndicate, Damascus, 1977 (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - I.D. Other exhibition material (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Subseries contains materials that seem to be related to exhibition activity
    - 1. Typescript text by Guido La Regina about Hammad, Damascus, 1965 (E-records AD_MC_091)
- Series II: Press clippings (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - II.A. Press clippings from the 1950s (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Series includes journal and newspaper coverage of group art exhibitions held in Damascus in which Hammad participated.
  - II.B. Press clippings from the 1960s (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Other artists discussed in the clippings include Nasir Shoura, Elias Zayat, Fateh al-Moudarres, Louay Kayali, among many others. A highlight are the more than 14 newspaper clippings detailing a major 1966 exhibition of Syrian painting at the Sursock Museum in Beirut, featuring debates about abstract painting.
  - II.C. Press clippings from the 1970s (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Highlights include features on Hammad published in the Syrian newspaper al-Thawra cultural supplement; growing coverage of al-Hurufiyya (or the use of Arabic letters in modern art) as an important art world development.
  - II.D. Press clippings from the 1980s, until the artist's death on August 11, 1988 (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Includes clippings from Syrian newspapers that cover annual art exhibitions and other major events in cultural life; features on Hammad that discuss his work; "Artists in Damascus," an illustrated article in Saudi Aramco World (1981).
  - II.E. Press clippings from 1988-present (collected posthumously) (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Includes tributes to the artist published in Syrian and Arab newspapers and journals.
  - II.F. Other press clippings and other press-related materials (undated, other) (E-records AD_MC_091)
- Series III: Writings by Hammad (published and unpublished) (E-records AD_MC_091)
  Includes the artist's notes from his own studies in Italy, educational resources he wrote in the context of the Faculty of Fine Arts, drafts of lectures, translations of lectures by foreign faculty (Guido La Regina) and guests (Nello Ponente), responses to journalists, and other writing.
- Series IV: Design work (E-records AD_MC_091)
  Designs and original drawings executed by Hammad, in ink and/or gouache, for use as book covers, illustrations in magazines, advertising (such as Walpamur paint company), and other clients and purposes.
  - IV.A. Book covers (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - IV.B. Magazine covers and other illustrations (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - IV.C. Commercial design for companies (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - IV.D. Poster, invitation, and card design (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - IV.E. Other designs (rugs and furniture; medals; other) (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - IV.F. Sketches for unspecified purposes (E-records AD_MC_091)
- Series V: Correspondence and personal papers (E-records AD_MC_091)
  Includes letters and postcards sent by the artist and received by the artist, official notices, memos, invitations to participate in events, permission forms.
- Series VI: Photographic materials (E-records AD_MC_091)
  - VI.A. Photographic prints (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Includes photographs of the artist and family; photographs of Hammad with students and colleagues at the Faculty of Fine Arts; photographs from travel, including many from the Accademia di Belle Arti in Rome (with fellow Syrian students such as Adham Ismail, Mamdouh Kashlan, and Ismail Husni, and Jordanian artist Mohanna Durra and Palestinian artist Ismail Shammout; and photographs of artworks by Hammad.
  - VI.B. Photographic slides (E-records AD_MC_091)
    Includes images of artwork by Hammad, including images from the inauguration of the Martyr's Monument he designed for Najha Cemetery outside Damascus; artwork by others, including exhibition shots from ​​Foundation Vasarely Aix-en-Provence; source images of historical events and figures.
- Series VII: Other items in the possession of the artist (E-records AD_MC_091)
  Includes postcards collected by the artist, likely as source material for art or as reference for lectures and other writing.